A Guide to the Personal Papers of Dr. Barnard DeJean Joy, 1950-1976
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Personal Papers of Bernard C. Joy, 1950-1976
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 70
11 boxes.
Joy, Dr. Barnard DeJean, 1908-1985
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Robert Comeau in 1994.
Biographical Information
Dr. Barnard DeJean Joy (1908-1985) was a graduate of Oregon State University and earned a Master's Degree in Agriculture from the University of Maryland and a doctorate in Adult Education from George Washington University. From 1930 to 1968 he was employed by the US Department of Agriculture. He served on the Arlington School Board from 1947-1963, and as chairman for 1948-1949, 1953 and 1960. He was also President of the Virginia School Boards Association, 1961-1962. For several years he taught an education course at George Washington University. He was chairman, 1965-1967, of the local board which organized Northern Virginia Community College, and was a founding board member of WETA-TV in Washington. After his retirement from the Department of Agriculture, he taught education courses at George Mason University and managed the University's grant-funded Community Education Program.
Scope and Content
RG 70 is collected and generated by Dr. Barnard D. Joy of Arlington, Virginia, in the course of his years of involvement in education in Virginia. The collection measures approximately 11.5 linear feet and contains material dating from 1950 to 1976. Types of material include: minutes, correspondence, clippings, newsletters, published and unpublished reports, grant proposals, narrative and financial reports, and course outlines, lectures, and examinations.
Subgroup 1, Arlington Schools, and Subgroup 2, Virginia Schools, contain chiefly printed reports on Arlington and Virginia education, 1951-1974, and have only scattered school board correspondence. Subgroup 3, National School Administration Groups, concerns school administrative associations, 1962-1965. Subgroup 4, Public Television, concerns WETA-TV and public television, 1955-1975. Subgroup 5, George Washington University, contains course material for a George Washington University course on school public relations. Subgroup 6, George Mason University, contains materials for courses taught at George Mason University, 1971-1975, and extensive documentation on the Community Education Program, including outlines for conferences on transportation, taxation and environmental issues. Subgroup 7, Northern Virginia Community College, contains scattered reports on the school, 1965-1967. S ubgroup 8, Virginia Higher Education Study Commission, contains published reports by the Virginia Higher Education Study Commission.
Arrangement
Record Group 70 is arranged into eight subgroups according to an area of activity or interest. Each subgroup is further divided into record series based on type of material, issues or associations.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Researchers interested in Arlington and Northern Virginia education issues will find complementary material in RG 7, Arlington Public Schools. For more information on one of Joy's colleagues on the School Board and at WETA, see RG 19, The Personal Papers of Elizabeth Pfohl Campbell.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Arlington Public Schools (Arlington, Va.); WETA (Radio station: Arlington, Va.); Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.)
Contents List
- Arlington Schools
  - Minutes
    - Arlington Citizen Participation Council, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
    - Committee to Develop a Five-Year Plan for Arlington Schools, Minutes, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
    - Reports of Committee to Develop a Five-Year Plan, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - Arlington Superintendent's Reports, 1951-1953 (Box 1)
    - Other Arlington School Reports, 1951-1968 (Box 1)
    - Report: "Current Litigation Seeking Integration of Drew and Hoffman-Boston Elementary Schools", 1971 (Box 1)
    - Proposed Five-Year Plan for ... Arlington Public Schools, 1975-1979 1975 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Arlington School Board Correspondence, 1957-1959 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence of Committee to Develop a Five-Year Plan for Arlington Schools, 1972-1974 (Box 1)
  - Notes, Newsletters, Clippings
    - Barnard Joy's Notes for Talks, 1954-1963 (Box 1)
    - Issues of Arlington School News, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Clippings, re: Schools, 1958 (Box 1)
- Virginia Schools
  - Reports
    - Reports of Virginia School Boards Association, 1958-1963 (Box 1)
    - Virginia State Board of Education Curriculum Committee Reports, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - Virginia Education Association Data on Virginia Schools, 1958-1960 (Box 1)
    - Other Published Reports on Virginia Schools, 1960-1972 (Box 1)
  - Barnard Joy's personal papers, re: School Board Association
    - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Notes for Talks, 1960s (Box 1)
- National School Administration Groups
  - American Association of School Administrators
    - Material on School Superintendent Selection, 1962-64 (Box 2)
    - Reports on Inservice Education, 1963 (Box 2)
    - Brochures from AASA, 1961 (Box 2)
    - AASA Committee for the Advancement of School Administration Meeting Agendas, 1962-1965 (1) (Box 2)
    - AASA Committee for the Advancement of School Administration Meeting Agendas, 1962-1965 (2) (Box 2)
    - AASA Committee for the Advancement of School Administration Meeting Agendas, 1962-1965 (3) (Box 2)
    - AASA Committee for the Advancement of School Administration Meeting Agendas, 1962-1965 (4) (Box 2)
    - AASA Committee for the Advancement of School Administration Meeting Agendas, 1962-1965 (5) (Box 2)
    - AASA/CASA Minutes, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - AASA/CASA Reports, 1962-1964 (1) (Box 2)
    - AASA/CASA Reports, 1962-1964 (2) (Box 2)
  - National School Boards Association
    - Minutes, 1962 (Box 2)
- Public Television
  - Northern Virginia Educational Television Association (NVETA)
    - Educational Television Planning Meetings, 1966-1968 (Box 3)
    - By-Laws, Chronologies, Policy Documents, Staff List, 1968-1970 (Box 3)
    - Executive Committee Minutes & Agendas, 1969-1975 (1) (Box 3)
    - Executive Committee Minutes & Agendas, 1969-1975 (2) (Box 3)
    - Executive Committee Minutes & Agendas, 1969-1975 (3) (Box 3)
    - Board of Directors Minutes, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
    - Planning Conference Materials, 1969 (Box 3)
    - General Meetings Minutes & Agendas, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Treasurer's Reports, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Budgets, Proposed & Approved, 1970-1971 (Box 3)
    - Financial Documents, 1971-1975 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1965-1975 (1) (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1965-1975 (2) (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1965-1975 (3) (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1965-1975 (4) (Box 4)
    - Annual Reports, 1969/1970, 1972/1973 (Box 4)
    - Printed Matter, 1967-1970 (Box 4)
    - WVNT53 Material, 1972-1974 (Box 4)
  - Greater Washington Educational Television Association (GWETA)
    - Constitution & Officers Lists, 1959-1962 (Box 4)
    - Minutes, 1956-1970 (1) (Box 4)
    - Minutes, 1956-1970 (2) (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1955-1970 (Box 4)
    - WETA Brochure, 1971 (Box 4)
    - General Educational Television Printed Matter, 1959-1963 (1) (Box 5)
    - General Educational Television Printed Matter, 1959-1963 (2) (Box 5)
    - Grant Proposal (Box 5)
- George Washington University
  - Educational Course Materials
    - Education 276 Course Outlines and Handouts, 1959-1961 (1) (Box 5)
    - Education 276 Course Outlines and Handouts, 1959-1961 (2) (Box 5)
    - Education 276 Course Outlines and Handouts, 1959-1961 (3) (Box 5)
    - Education 276 Lectures, 1959-1961 (Box 5)
    - Education 276 Study Problems, 1961 (Box 5)
    - Education 276 Tests & Examinations, 1959-1961 (Box 5)
- George Mason University
  - Graduate Education Courses
    - Proposal for a Master's Degree Program (Box 5)
    - Plans for Education 507, 1971-1976 (1) (Box 5)
    - Plans for Education 507, 1971-1976 (2) (Box 5)
    - Plans for Education 507, 1971-1976 (3) (Box 5)
    - Plans for Education 507, 1971-1976 (4) (Box 5)
    - Plans for Education 507, 1971-1976 (5) (Box 5)
    - Advisory Committee for Education 507, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Staff Lists & Correspondence for Education 507, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Ed. 507 Course Schedule, 1972 (Box 5)
    - Ed. 507 Registration Information, 1972 (Box 5)
    - Ed. 507 Reference Readings, 1971-1974 (Box 5)
    - Ed. 507 Secretary's Reports, 1974 (Box 6)
    - Ed. 507 Teamwork Projects, 1973 (Box 6)
    - Ed. 507 Problem Solving Project, 1973-1974 (Box 6)
    - Ed. 507 Evaluation Plan, 1973 (Box 6)
    - Ed. 507 Examination Questions, 1971-1974 (Box 6)
    - Ed. 507 Tests, 1972-1974 (Box 6)
    - Topic File 1, 1972-1976 (Box 6)
    - Topic File 2, 1972-1976 (Box 6)
    - Topic File 3, 1972-1976 (Box 6)
    - Topic File 4, 1972-1976 (Box 6)
    - Topic File 5, 1972-1976 (Box 6)
    - Topic File 6, 1972-1976 (Box 6)
    - Topic File 7, 1972-1976 (Box 6)
    - Topic File 8, 1972-1976 (Box 6)
    - Topic File 9, 1972-1976 (Box 6)
    - Topic File 10, 1972-1976 (Box 6)
    - Topic File 11, 1972-1976 (Box 6)
    - Topic File 12, 1972-1976 (Box 6)
    - Topic File 13, 1972-1976 (Box 6)
    - Topic File 14, 1972-1976 (Box 6)
    - Topic File 15, 1972-1976 (Box 6)
    - News Release, re: Ed. 507, 1974 (Box 6)
    - Teacher Salary Analysis for Ed. 507 (Box 6)
    - "Community Relations Activities of Northern Virginia Schools" by Barnard Joy (Box 6)
    - Resource Materials for Ed. 507, 1951-1954 (Box 6)
    - Resource Materials for Ed. 507, 1955-1956 (Box 7)
    - Resource Materials for Ed. 507, 1957-1958 (Box 7)
    - Resource Materials for Ed. 507, 1959-1974 (Box 7)
  - GMU Community Education Program Materials
    - Title I Higher Education Act of 1965 Information, 1971-1975 (Box 7)
    - Title VIII Information Documents, 1969-1970 (Box 7)
    - Mission & Goals, George Mason University, 1971-1975 (Box 7)
    - GMU Community Service Program Description (Box 7)
    - GMU Community Education Grant Proposals, 1969-1970 (Box 7)
    - GMU Community Education Grant Proposals, 1971 (Box 7)
    - GMU Community Education Grant Proposals, 1972 (Box 7)
    - GMU Community Education Grant Proposals, 1973 (Box 7)
    - GMU Community Education Grant Proposals, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
    - Financial Documents: GMU Community Education Program, 1968-1970 (Box 8)
    - Financial Documents: GMU Community Education Program, 1971-1972 (Box 8)
    - Financial Documents: GMU Community Education Program, 1973-1975 (Box 8)
    - GMU Community Education Program Narrative Reports, 1967-1970 (Box 8)
    - GMU Community Education Program Narrative Reports, 1971-1972 (Box 8)
    - GMU Community Education Program Narrative Reports, 1973-1975 (Box 8)
    - GMU Community Education Program Correspondence, n.d. (Box 8)
    - GMU Community Education Program Correspondence, 1967-1970 (Box 8)
    - GMU Community Education Program Correspondence, January - June 1971 (Box 8)
    - GMU Community Education Program Correspondence, July - December 1971 (Box 8)
    - GMU Community Education Program Correspondence, 1972 (Box 8)
    - GMU Community Education Program Correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 8)
    - "Applying Principles of Supervision" Planning Papers, 1970 (Box 8)
    - "Citizen Participation in Planning for More Effective Use of Resources," 1971 (Box 8)
    - "Community Economic Health" (Box 8)
    - "Economics and Politics of Balanced Transportation for Northern Virginia," 1972 (1) (Box 8)
    - "Economics and Politics of Balanced Transportation for Northern Virginia," 1972 (2) (Box 9)
    - "Economics and Politics of Balanced Transportation for Northern Virginia," 1972 (3) (Box 9)
    - "Environment and Development," 1971 (1) (Box 9)
    - "Environment and Development," 1971 (2) (Box 9)
    - "Erosion and Siltation Control," 1970 (Box 9)
    - "Fairfax County Goals," 1971 (Box 9)
    - "Financing Local Government," 1971 (Box 9)
    - "Growth and Its Implications," 1971 (1) (Box 9)
    - "Growth and Its Implications," 1971 (Box 9)
    - "Growth Issues," 1973-1974 (1) (Box 9)
    - "Growth Issues," 1973-1974 (2) (Box 9)
    - "Health Care: Whose Business?" 1972 (Box 9)
    - "Improving Real Property Tax," 1972 (Box 9)
    - "Intergovernmental Cooperation in Northern Virginia" (Box 10)
    - "Local-State Financing of Services," 1972 (Box 10)
    - "More Effective Communication" (Box 10)
    - "Transportation Problems," 1972-1975 (Box 10)
    - "Understanding Employee-Management Relations," 1972 (Box 10)
    - "Volunteers in Public Schools," 1970 (1) (Box 10)
    - "Volunteers in Public Schools," 1970 (2) (Box 10)
    - "Volunteers in Public Schools," 1970 (3) (Box 10)
  - Other Community Education Programs
    - Other Conferences in Northern Virginia, 1967-1971 (Box 10)
    - Mid-Atlantic Center for Community Education Brochures, 1973-1974 (Box 10)
    - Northern Virginia Regional Council for Continuing Education: Plans, Correspondence, Minutes, 1970-1972 (Box 10)
- Northern Virginia Community College
  - Virginia Senate Bill to Create Department of Community Colleges, 1966
    - Bill Text (Box 10)
  - NOVA Community College Board of Trustees
    - Agendas, Minutes and Correspondence, 1966 (Box 10)
  - Printed Matter
    - Reports on NOVA Community College, 1965 (Box 10)
    - Dedication Programs, 1965 (Box 10)
    - Issues of "Galaxy", 1966 (Box 10)
- Virginia Higher Education Study Commission
  - Staff Reports & Other Reports
    - Report 4: "The Two-Year College in Virginia" 1965 (Box 10)
    - Report 6: "Educational Programs in Virginia for Fields Related to Health" 1965 (Box 10)
    - Report 7: "Extension Services, Television Instruction and Research in Virginia Institutions of Higher Education" 1965 (Box 11)
    - Report 8: "The Faculties of Virginia's Colleges and Universities" 1965 (Box 11)
    - Report 9: "Library Services in Virginia's Institutions of Higher Education" 1965 (Box 11)
    - Report 10: "Instructional Plant Facilities in Virginia's Institutions of Higher Education" 1965 (Box 11)
    - Report 11: "Control and Coordination of Higher Education in Virginia" 1965 (Box 11)
    - "Focus on Northern Virginia: Design for Urban Planning and Development Policies" 1971 (Box 11)